Bengali Oral Histories MS165
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Bengali Oral Histories
2006 -- 2013
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Manjapra, Kris, 1979-
MS165
200 Digital Object(s) 160 unprocessed digital objects
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series: Bengali Oral Histories; Corpora; Additional accessions.
Biographical / Historical
Kris Manjapra (1978-) was born in Nassau, Bahamas on July 28, 1978. He joined the Tufts University history department in 2008 after completing his dissertation at Harvard in 2007 and a postdoctoral year at UCLA. At Tufts he teaches courses on South Asia and globalization, comparative anti-colonialism, South Asian and modern European intellectual history, and post-colonialism. Manjapra's research is on South Asian and German history, with a focus on transnational and post-colonial perspectives.
As co-director of the South Asia Digital Humanities Lab at Tufts, Manjapra organizes the Corpora multimedia archiving project that aims to create an indexed and federated repository of oral histories, lectures, and other educational audio-visual materials across disciplines.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains oral histories, transcripts, and images recorded with senior intellectuals from West Bengal and Bangladesh who were born in the years from 1920 to c. 1950. This collection provides the opportunity to explore South Asian history in ways that problematize national and regional frames of historical analysis. Interviewees reflect on historical events from the era of freedom struggle to the rise of nation-states, including the partition of India and Pakistan in 1947, and the creation of Bangladesh in 1971. Interviewees also speak about continuities, breaks and new developments in the intellectual history of the Bengal region, and of South Asia more generally from the 1920s to the 1970s. This project has been funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities and by the Berger Family Digital Humanities Grant.
Bangladesh; Oral history; Faculty research
- Bengali Oral Histories, 2006 -- 2011; MS165.001; 27 Digital Object(s)
  Conditions Governing Access
  75 years from the date of creation. Open for research.
  - Oral history interview with Tapan Raychaudhuri, 2008-06-18; MS165.001.001.00001; Raychaudhuri, Tapan; Manjapra, Kris
    Open for research.
    Scope and Contents
    Interviewed in Oxford, United Kingdom by Kris Manjapra
    India; South Asia; West Bengal (India); Bangladesh; Intellectual history; Personal narratives; Decolonization; Postcolonialism; Independence movements; Oral history; Bengali Intellectuals Oral History Project
  - Oral history interview with Barid Barun Chatterjee, 2007-07-29; MS165.001.002.00001; Chatterjee, Barid Barun; Manjapra, Kris
    Interviewed in Kolkata, West Bengal, India by Kris Manjapra
  - Oral history interview with Andre Beteille, 2009-08-14; MS165.001.003.00001; Beteille, Andre; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Krishna Bose, 2009-08-09; MS165.001.004.00001; Bose, Krishna; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Satyesh Chakrabarty, 2009-08-22; MS165.001.005.00001; Chakrabarty, Satyesh; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Kamal Datta, 2009-08-20; MS165.001.008.00001; Datta, Kamal; Manjapra, Kris
    Interviewed in Delhi, India by Kris Manjapra
  - Oral history interview with Barun De, 2007-12-16; MS165.001.009.00001; De, Barun; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Ranajit Guha, 2009-07-29; MS165.001.010.00001; Guha, Ranajit; Manjapra, Kris
    75 years from date of creation.
    Interviewed in Vienna, Austria by Kris Manjapra
  - Oral history interview with Partha Mitter, 2006-06-18; MS165.001.011.00001; Mitter, Partha; Manjapra, Kris
    75 years from the date of creation.
  - Oral history interview with Sibnarayan Ray, 2007-12-12; MS165.001.012.00001; Ray, Sibnarayan; Manjapra, Kris
    Interviewed in Shantiniketan, West Bengal by Kris Manjapra
  - Oral history interview with Prasanta Ray, 2009-08-12; MS165.001.013.00001; Ray, Prasanta; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Swarajbrata Sengupta, 2009-08-22; MS165.001.014.00001; Sengupta, Swarajbrata; Iqbal, Iftekhar
  - Oral history interview with Anissuzaman, 2009-10-25; MS165.001.016.00001; Anissuzaman; Iqbal, Iftekhar
    Interviewed in Dhaka, Bangladesh by Iftekhar Iqbal
  - Oral history interview with Badruddin Umar, 2009-11-25; MS165.001.017.00001; Umar, Badruddin; Iqbal, Iftekhar
  - Oral history interview with Amartya Sen, 2010-02-01; MS165.001.019.00001; Sen, Amartya; Manjapra, Kris
    Interviewed in Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America by Kris Manjapra
  - Oral history interview with Amiya Bagchi, 2010-01-11; MS165.001.020.00001; Bagchi, Amiya; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Nabaneeta Dev Sen, 2010-01-09; MS165.001.021.00001; Sen, Nabaneeta Dev; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Sankha Ghosh, 2010-01-12; MS165.001.022.00001; Ghosh, Sankha; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Jharna Gourlay, 2010-01-08; MS165.001.023.00001; Gourlay, Jharna; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Jotirmoy Pal Chaudhuri, 2009-12-28; MS165.001.024.00001; Chaudhuri, Jotirmoy Pal; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Aloke Ranjan Dasgupta, 2010-01-13; MS165.001.025.00001; Dasgupta, Aloke Ranjan; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Purushotamm Lal, 2010-01-12; MS165.001.026.00001; Lal, Purushotamm; Manjapra, Kris
  - Oral history interview with Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak, 2010-08-25; MS165.001.027.00001; Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty; Manjapra, Kris
    Interviewed in Columbia University, New York, New York, United States of America by Kris Manjapra
  - Oral history interview with Uma Dasgupta, 2010-01-10; MS165.001.028.00001; Dasgupta, Uma; Iqbal, Iftekhar
  - Oral history interview with AF Salahuddin Ahmed, 2011-05-24; MS165.001.029.00001; Ahmed, AF Salahuddin; Iqbal, Iftekhar
  - Oral history interview with Jyotirmoy Datta, 2010-08-23; MS165.001.039.00001; Datta, Jyotirmoy; Iqbal, Iftekhar
    Interviewed in Hillsborough, New Jersey, United States of America by Kris Manjapra
  - Oral history interview with Ashin Datta, 2010-01-08; MS165.001.041.00001; Datta, Ashin; Iqbal, Iftekhar
- Corpora, 2011 -- 2013; MS165.002; 13 Digital Object(s)
  - Robert Kaplan in discussion with Sugata Bose, 2012-03-01; MS165.002.001.00001; Kaplan, Robert D., 1952-; Bose, Sugata; Manjapra, Kris
    Robert Kaplan, author of Monsoon: The Indian Ocean and the Future of American Power (Random House 2010), in discussion with Sugata Bose (Gardiner Professor of Oceanic History and Affairs, Harvard University).
    Islam on the Indian Ocean Rim
  - Dr. Tim Harper, Singapore 1915 and the Birth of the Asian Underground, 2013-03-05; MS165.002.001.00002; Harper, T. N. (Timothy Norman), 1965-
    Dr. Tim Harper, Centre for History and Economics, Magdalene College, Cambridge University. Lecture entitled "Singapore 1915 and the Birth of the Asian Underground"
  - Robert Travers, The Connected World of Haji Mustapha: an informer to the British in eighteenth century Bengal, 2012-11-15; MS165.002.001.00003; Travers, Robert, 1972-
    Robert Travers, Assoc. Professor, Dept. of History, Cornell University. Lecture entitled "The Connected World of Haji Mustapha: an informer to the British in eighteenth century Bengal"
  - William Dalrymple, Return of a King: Shah Shuja and the First Anglo-Afghan War 1839-42, 2012-04-10; MS165.002.001.00004; Dalrymple, William
    William Dalrymple lecture entitled "Return of a King: Shah Shuja and the First Anglo-Afghan War 1839-42"
  - Sana Aiyar, Trade and Politics in a Diasporic Milieu: Colonial Kenya's South Asians, 2012-02-16; MS165.002.001.00005; Aiyar, Sana
    Sana Aiyar lecture entitled "Trade and Politics in a Diasporic Milieu: Colonial Kenya's South Asians"
  - Sunil Amrith, Islam in the Bay of Bengal: Between Tamil and Malay Worlds, 2011-11-14; MS165.002.001.00006; Amrith, Sunil S.
    Sunil Amrith lecture entitled "Islam in the Bay of Bengal: Between Tamil and Malay Worlds"
    Bay of Bengal
  - Jonathan Spencer, Peeling the Onion of Conflict: Muslims (and Catholics and Buddhists and Others) in the Sri Lankan Civil War, 2012-03-27; MS165.002.001.00007; Spencer, Jonathan, 1954-
    Jonathan Spencer lecture entitled "Peeling the Onion of Conflict: Muslims (and Catholics and Buddhists and Others) in the Sri Lankan Civil War"
  - Partha Chatterjee, Early Modern Absolutism in 18th Century India, 2011-12-10; MS165.002.001.00008; Chatterjee, Partha, 1947-
    Partha Chatterjee lecture entitled "Early Modern Absolutism in 18th Century India"
  - Willem van Schendel, Chittagong in Four Scenes: Spatial Moments at the Indian Ocean's Edge (1600-2010s), 2013-09-11; MS165.002.001.00009; Schendel, Willem van
    Willem van Schendel lecture entitled "Chittagong in Four Scenes: Spatial Moments at the Indian Ocean's Edge (1600-2010s)"
  - Seema Alavi, Mughal Decline and the emergence of new global connections in early modern India, 2011-10-26; MS165.002.001.00010; Alavi, Seema
    Seema Alavi lecture entitled "Mughal Decline and the emergence of new global connections in early modern India"
  - Eric Tagliacozzo, Hajj in the Time of Cholera: Pilgrim Ships and Contagion from Southeast Asia to the Red Sea, 2011-12-07; MS165.002.001.00011; Tagliacozzo, Eric
    Eric Tagliacozzo lecture entitled Hajj in the Time of Cholera: Pilgrim Ships and Contagion from Southeast Asia to the Red Sea
  - Enseng Ho, Burial and Travel: Islam across Indian Ocean Cultures, 2011-09-28; MS165.002.001.00012; Ho, Enseng
    Enseng Ho lecture entitled Burial and Travel: Islam across Indian Ocean Cultures.
  - Nile Green, An Economy of Enchantment: Markets for Islam in an Industrializing Ocean, 2012-02-09; MS165.002.001.00013; Green, Nile
    Nile Green lecture entitled "An Economy of Enchantment: Markets for Islam in an Industrializing Ocean."
- Additional accessions, 2010 -- 2011; MS165.003; 1 Digital Object(s)
  160 images
  - Images, 2010 -- 2011; MS165-001